<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of Mr Burroughes, against Mr Edwards his foule aspersions, in his spreading Gangræna, and his angry Antiapologia. Concluding with a briefe declaration what the Independents would have. / By Jer: Burroughes.</title>
            <author>Burroughs, Jeremiah, 1599-1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 80 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78005</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B6126</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E345_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200993</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861589</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861589</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113727</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78005)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113727)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 56:E345[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of Mr Burroughes, against Mr Edwards his foule aspersions, in his spreading Gangræna, and his angry Antiapologia. Concluding with a briefe declaration what the Independents would have. / By Jer: Burroughes.</title>
                  <author>Burroughs, Jeremiah, 1599-1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Overton, and are to be sold at his shop at the entring into Popes-head Alley out of Lumbard-street.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXLVI. [1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to "Gangræna" (Wing E228) and "Antapologia" (Wing E222) by Thomas Edwards.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 23".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Edwards, Thomas, 1599-1647. --  Gangræna --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Edwards, Thomas, 1599-1647. --  Antapologia --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113727:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:113727:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHES,</hi> Againſt M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> EDWARDS his foule Aſperſions, in his ſpreading <hi>Gangraena,</hi> and his angry <hi>Antiapologia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concluding with A BRIEFE DECLARATION What the INDEPENDENTS would have.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JER: BURROUGHES.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>JER. 20.10.</bibl>
               <p>Report, ſay they, and we will report.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>PROV. 18.8.</bibl>
               <p>The words of a tale-bearer are as wounds, and they go downe into the innermoſt parts of the belly.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Tertul. adverſ. Hermogenem.</bibl>
               <p>Hermogenes natura turbulentus, qui loquacitatem facundiam exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimet, &amp; impudentiam conſtantiam deputet, &amp; maledicere ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulis officium bonae conſcientiae judicet.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Overton,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the entring into Popes-head Alley out of Lumbard-ſtreet. MDCXLVI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:113727:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113727:2"/>
            <head>A Vindication of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Burroughes,</hi> Againſt M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his foul Aſperſions.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I may venture upon the teſtimony of the conſciences of thoſe who know me, to vindicate me from M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his foule aſperſions;<note place="margin">Nec audiendi ſunt quando reprehenſa in aliquo negligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ſua, per qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fit ut in malam ſuſpicionem ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant, unde ſua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vitam longe ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſſe ſciunt, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunt ſibi coram Deo ſufficere conſcientiam, exiſtimationem hominum non imprudenter ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, verumetia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crudeliter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temnentes. Quiſquis à cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minibus vitam ſuam cuſtodit, ſibi bene facit; quiſquis etiam famam, &amp; in alios miſericors eſt, nobis neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaria eſt vita noſtra, aliis fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. <hi>Aug. de bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no viduitatis, c. 22.</hi>
               </note> yet hearing there are ſome whoſe ſpirits are as dryed tinder to his ſire, (if men were willing to be undeceived, and not to runne away with fooliſh conceits.) I thought it might not be amiſſe to ſpend an houre or two upon this vaine man. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſayes, <hi>Thoſe are not to be hearkned to, who having ſuſpition raiſed of them which they know themſelves to be free of, ſhall ſay, their conſcience in the preſence of God is enough for them, and for the eſteeme of men doe not onely imprudently contemne, but in it are cruell:</hi> That is, as he after expreſſes himſelfe againſt others which are hindred in the good they might get by them, becauſe the ſuſpition raiſed is not removed: For, ſayes he, <hi>A good life is neceſſary for our ſelves, but a good fame for others. You doe well to your ſelfe in being carefull of your life, but you are mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to others in being carefull of your name.</hi> Wherefore though mine owne conſcience is enough to ſatisfie my ſelfe againſt what ever M. <hi>Edwards</hi> hath written or ſaid, yet in mercy to others, and that I may not be wanting to my duty in removing any ſtumbling block that might hinder the work of my Miniſtery, which I was moved unto by a Letter ſent to me from a good and worthy friend, I ſhall now doe that which I had thought I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have brought my heart unto, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſpend time in the vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication of my ſelfe. Might the hurt goe no farther then my ſelfe, if I did not doe it, the meaneſt imployment in the world ſhould rather take up my time then this, but ſomething muſt be done.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113727:3"/>
               <hi>John</hi> was of a moſt loving, ſweet, and gentle temper, yet having to deale with a man of an evill ſpirit, he ſpeaks contemptuouſly of him, <hi>I will remember</hi> (ſaies he) <hi>his deeds,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, prating againſt us with malicious words. Such a naughty ſpirit appeares in this man; ſo be it he can get filth to caſt upon men, he cares not out of what kennel he rakes it; as it is hard to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with him, to anſwer him according to his folly without ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions againſt him, grievous to a ſpirit that hath any ſweetneſſe of love, or meekneſſe in it; had I to deale with him alone, I ſhould onely anſwer him in the words of the Angel, <hi>Jude</hi> 9. <hi>The Lord rebuke thee.</hi> Yet the man is very impatient that he hath no An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, he concludes, and would have others to doe ſo too, that all he ſayes is truth, becauſe there comes forth no Anſwer to it. It is a miſerable thing that we muſt be at the mercy of every one, who hath a mind to accuſe and rayle, ſo as to be bound to take off our ſelves from whatſoever imployments God hath ſet us about, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the anſwering of whatſoever he ſayes or writes; I hope I ſhall give God a better account of my time then ſo. Whatſoever M. <hi>Edwards</hi> hath written or ſaid concerning me, I bleſſe God I can with comfort ſpread it before him, and intreat him to judge betweene us.</p>
            <p>He thinkes he hath done God and his Bretheren good ſervice, but I am very confident, and I am not alone in this my confidence, that Biſhop <hi>Wren</hi> was not more miſchievous to the Prelacy, then he hath beene to the Presbytery; I doubt whether there ever was any in the Chriſtian world who was looked upon as a man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing godlineſſe in that height that he hath beene, that ever ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted ſo much boldneſſe and malice againſt ſuch as himſelfe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges to be godly, as he hath done; Were there nothing but the Presbyteriall opinion that made the difference betweene him and me, I ſhould not abate my eſteeme of his godlineſſe in the leaſt, for I beleeve there are as godly Presbyterians as Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents. But that fiery rage, that implacable irrationall violence of his, makes me ſtand and wonder at him, not ſo much for recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtories that he hears, but that hearing ſuch vile reproachfull things againſt ſuch as he ownes to be godly, and the perſons thus reproched living neare him in the City, who it may be might ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy him in the falſneſſe of the reports, ſo as to keepe him from
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:113727:3"/>publiſhing them, yea when ſome of them hearing what he was about, have ſent to him to tell him that if he would Confer with them they would ſatisfy him about particulars they would clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convince him, that ſuch men were traduced, and himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed in ſuch reports, yet that he ſhould refuſe to confer with them, ſaying he had teſtimony enough, and ſo fall a laying on, take off who will or can, herein following that wicked Jeſuiticall Maxime, <hi>Fortiter calumniare, aliquid haerebit,</hi> Calumniate luſtily, boldly, no matter whether it be true or falſe, ſomthing will ſtick. I beleeve this example can hardly be paralleld in any age. How is it poſſible that he ſhould ever right thoſe he has wronged, if he ſaies he will recant if he can be convinced wherein any is wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? That will not doe it, for how is he ſure that his recantation ſhall come to the knowledge of all, to whom his calumniation hath come? is this enough for mens names ſo traduced by him, for him afterwards to ſay. I was told ſo, I was miſinformed? I beſeech God to touch his heart, and the hearts of ſuch as have any way encouraged him in ſuch a foule worke.</p>
            <p>There is an odious diſeaſe in nature, caſting up the excrementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious filthineſſe at the mouth, which is no leſſe noyſome then dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, therefore the Phyſitians call it <hi>Miſerere mei Deus.</hi> Thus exulcerate minds affected with the like malady in morality, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſurcharged with ſuperfluity of choler and malice, and not able to containe, break forth into diſtemper of words, and poure it out in unſavoury language; ſuch we muſt leave to a <hi>Miſerere mei.</hi> But is M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſick of this diſeaſe? Doth not he profeſſe his zeale for God, his dependance upon God for aſſiſtance very often?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Yes he doth, but I feare he takes Gods name much in vain in ſo doing; ſet aſide the difference of his judgement, I cannot beleeve that God will ever owne that way he takes; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath that filthy diſeaſe mentioned, if you can endure to look upon the loathſome ſtuffe that comes from him, you may eaſily judge; if I ſhould relate much of it, it would be nauſeous. I will give you one inſtance. In the firſt page of his Preface to the firſt part of his <hi>Gangrana,</hi> he ſpeaks of Printed pamphlets, where he ſayes he was reproached, but he was not willing to be provoked, or to trouble himſelfe at the barking of every dog;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113727:4"/>and for this he quotes in his margin M. <hi>Woodward,</hi> and M. <hi>Burton.</hi> What is M. <hi>Burton</hi> become a dog now, and M. <hi>Woodward,</hi> who is a knowne ancient godly man, a Schoolmaſter, yet for ought I know no Independent, is he a dog in M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his mouth and pen? If M. <hi>Edwards</hi> and his party riſe in their ſpirits according to this proportion, how can we live neere them? what already got ſo above M. <hi>Woodward</hi> and M. <hi>Burton,</hi> even whilſt they are but in the ſhell, and ſee power but hopefully to come into their hands, that they can looke upon them as dogs beneath them? I ſpeak of M. <hi>Edwards</hi> and his party, becauſe he ſayes ſo many have given him thanks for his Book.</p>
            <p>In his laſt booke I finde him exceedingly fretting and vexing at a teſtimony Maſter <hi>John Goodwin</hi> had under my hand againſt the truth of a ſtory in his <hi>Grangraena,</hi> which he ſayes is full of Jeſuiticall equivocation. Yea further, no equivocation can free it from a lye. <hi>Bona verba.</hi> After maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> hath done fretting and chafing, after his fit is over, notwithſtanding all he hath ſaid, that teſtimony is, and muſt ſtand true, and will be found in the plainneſſe of it to be a witneſſe againſt him: what! beyond equivocation? no leſſe then a flat lye. This is the firſt time that ever any man gave me the lye. But I pray Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> how doe you know it is a lye? How? Maſter <hi>Allen</hi> (he miſtakes the mans name, the man he means is Maſter <hi>Alle</hi>) an honeſt underſtanding man he ſaies told him ſo, and after juſtifyed it in Maſter <hi>Bellamies</hi> ſhop in the preſence of many; This is the onely witneſſe Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> hath againſt me: as for Maſter <hi>Randal</hi> whom he mentions, he ſpeaks onely of <hi>Nicols</hi> his being with M. <hi>Greenhil</hi> at another time, not of that meeting I te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie againſt, nor any thing about my knowledge of him, nor any thing that Maſter <hi>Greenhill</hi> denyes. Howſoever then it is but ones I, and ones No: and yet how many have drunk in this report as dirty and foule as it is? ſurely there is a ſpirit in men that makes them very thirſty after Calumnies and reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. But what if this onely witneſſe M. <hi>Edwards</hi> hath to prove me a Lyar, ſhall give it under his hand that that teſtimony of mine is true, what if that which M. <hi>Edwards</hi> in the ſtrength of that witneſſe ſhall ſay is a lye, I ſhall be able in the ſtrength of the ſame witneſſe, ſay is true; where will the lye ſtick then? After
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113727:4"/>M. <hi>Iohn Goodwins</hi> Book came out, I met with this M. <hi>Alle,</hi> and in the preſence of many, cauſed him to turne to that page where my teſtimony is, and to read it; I then asked him, Whether that teſtimony of mine were true or not? He anſwered, for any thing he knew it was true. Some in the company deſired him to ſet his hand to what he ſaid; He preſently tooke pen and inke, ſaying, he would write according to what he apprehended, and ſo farre as he knew, and wrote theſe words, ſubſcribing his name:</p>
            <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="affidavit">
               <body>
                  <p>That the Teſtimony of M. <hi>Burroughes</hi> which M. <hi>John Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win,</hi> pag. 42. ſaith he hath under his hand about <hi>Nicols,</hi> is true.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thomas Alle.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>I have by me the paper where this is written with his owne hand, and this M. <hi>Alle,</hi> M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his onely witneſſe, in the preſence of many, under his hand, witneſſes that he thinks my te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony true, in reference to the whole I had written to M. <hi>Iohn Goodwin.</hi> By what witneſſe then can M. <hi>Edwards</hi> prove a lye? Something hath cauſed M. <hi>Alle</hi> ſince to mince the matter, and to make a relation of ſome things that neither I nor M. <hi>Greenhill</hi> ownes, but at that time when he gave my juſtification under his hand, he was urged againe and againe in the preſence of many to declare whether he could ſay any thing againſt the truth of any particular in my teſtimony, and he profeſſed he could not. Surely if he could not, how could M. <hi>Edwards</hi> who had all he had from him? Beſides this, M. <hi>Alle</hi> ſayes in what he hath printed, that there are ſome things in M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his Book, (ſpeaking in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to what M. <hi>Edwards</hi> reports from him) that never came from him; and yet M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſtands boldly to juſtifie that all from firſt to laſt is true. But I pray conſider further what are M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his arguments to prove my teſtimony a lye.</p>
            <p>Firſt this. I ſay the ſtory of <hi>Nicols</hi> and ſuch a meeting mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>pag.</hi> 79. is all falſe. No, ſayes he, ſome part is true. The firſt part wherin is laid down <hi>Nicols</hi> his maintaining to M. <hi>Greenhils</hi> face thoſe opinions; How then came M. <hi>Burroughes</hi> his affirming that ſtory M. <hi>Edwards</hi> hath of one <hi>Nicols</hi> to be falſe, be in any ſenſe juſtified to be true?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> See the ſagacity of the man: Take heed what you ſay
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113727:5"/>againſt M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> he is cunning, he will find you out. But M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> looke back againe to what I affirme in that teſtimony under my hand, you ſhall find, I onely ſay this, that all the ſtory a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Nicols</hi> in ſuch a page, namely <hi>pag.</hi> 79. is falſe, now to prove me a lyar you tell the world that a part of the ſtory in another <hi>pag.</hi> namely <hi>pag.</hi> 78. is true, is this a good argument to prove a man a lyar, who ſaies the ſtory in one <hi>pag.</hi> of a booke is falſe? But he lyes, becauſe the ſtory of another page of the booke is true? What brave ſtuffe is here to prove a lye? I profeſſe to all the world, as in the preſence of God, I doe not now invent this to help to ſalve the buſineſſe, but what ever failing might be in the expreſſion, the reaſon of my mentioning the page, was to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit my teſtimony to what was in that page concerning <hi>Nicols;</hi> what was in that meeting there mentioned in reference to him, I took not upon me to deny what might be between M. <hi>Greenhill</hi> and <hi>Nicols</hi> at ſome other time; and all that M. <hi>Greenhill</hi> denyes in my teſtimony is that part of the ſtory of <hi>Nicols,</hi> in reference to that meeting there mentioned. He need not rub his memory to call to mind any other time that <hi>Nicols</hi> had been with him; for where did he ever deny any ſuch thing? There is nothing men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned about it in any thing I wrote to M. <hi>John Goodwin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you have M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his firſt argument to prove a lye; let us ſee whether he will be more happy in his ſecond: will he not there hit the nayle on the head? It is this. How can M. <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes</hi> ſay he never heard of ſuch a man in the world as <hi>Nicols,</hi> when as it cannot be thought but that M. <hi>Greenhill</hi> named him to him at Col. <hi>Zacharies</hi> houſe?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> The Argument runnes thus, Maſter <hi>Burroughes</hi> ſaies he never heard of <hi>Nicols,</hi> but he lies, becauſe it cannot be thought but that Maſter <hi>Greenhil</hi> named him to him. If I ſhould argue from all mens thoughts, expreſſed about Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> and beleeve them, I could prove Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> foule enough.</p>
            <p>His 3. Argument, if I never heard of <hi>Nicols,</hi> how came Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Alle</hi> to know, that the opinions related, were <hi>Nicols</hi> his opinions, ſeeing Maſter <hi>Alle</hi> was not at the firſt meeting? <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe Maſter <hi>Alle</hi> had heard of <hi>Nicols,</hi> therefore I lye in ſaying I never heard of him, what ridiculous ſtuffe is this?</p>
            <p n="4">4. How can Maſter <hi>Burroughes</hi> give it under his hand that he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113727:5"/>to this day never know of any of <hi>Nicols</hi> his opinions, when the opinions of <hi>Nicols</hi> were told him by Maſter <hi>Greenhil? Anſ.</hi> But can Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> or any man living thinke that I denyed that I had never heard of ſuch an opinion that makes God to be the Author of ſin? which it ſeems was <hi>Nicols</hi> his opinion; ſurely both I and all men that know what the ſtudy of Divinity meanes have heard 100. times of this opinion. M. <hi>Greenhil</hi> ſpeakes of Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous opinions and names this, does it follow therfore that he told me of <hi>Nicols</hi> his opinions? I appeal to 100. Divines in London, have ye ever heard of <hi>Nicols</hi> in Moore-fields and his damnable opinions, would they not ſtay till we read Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> his booke we never heard of <hi>Nicols</hi> and his opinions, and yet not one of theſe but have heard that ſome hold God to be the Author of ſinne, but they would tell you any man but a cavilling wrangler would ſay the meaning of the words muſt needs be, that they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard of this opinion as <hi>Nicols</hi> his opinion.</p>
            <p>What brave worke is here to prove a lye! If theſe be good proofs of a lye, I onely ſay this, if Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> can make lyes as faſt as he can prove them, he hath wonne the honour of the name <hi>Cretenſis,</hi> and deſerves to carry it written in a paper in his hat all his dayes.</p>
            <p>For equivocation his Quere is <hi>pag.</hi> 92. <hi>Whether any Jeſuite could or would have drawne up halfe a ſcore lines fuller of equive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> yet in the page before he ſaies I put all I ſay upon thoſe words, a meeting and ſuch a meeting concluded of, which words <hi>meeting</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> are mentioned Sixe times a peece brought in at every turne; all the weight of his teſtimony ſtill referring to the words <hi>meeting</hi> and <hi>ſuch, ſuch a meeting, ſuch a man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Truly I did mention thoſe words, <hi>ſuch a meeting, ſuch a man,</hi> often, on purpoſe that the Reader might know that all I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended was in reference to that meeting, and to <hi>Nicols</hi> as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in it; But he ſayes my equivocation lies in this, that I would put the whole ſtory upon that meeting.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> If M. <hi>Edwards</hi> were not reſolved to ſhut his eyes, hee might ſee that I onely meddle with that of the ſtory that is menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in ſuch a page, namely page 79. I ſay all that is falſe, but if there be any thing true of the ſtory in another page, I meddle not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113727:6"/>with it: If I had ſaid all the ſtory had beene falſe, without limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to that page, M. <hi>Edwards</hi> had had roome enough to have ruffled in, and yet he ruffles as if I had ſaid ſo, and would make the world beleeve I did ſay ſo.</p>
            <p>He ſayes <hi>pag.</hi> 88. that the whole ſtory and all the particulare of it are true, and there is nothing falſe in it from firſt to laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> What impudence is here, when his onely witneſſe to that ſtory ſayes what I have ſaid in denying that which is <hi>page</hi> 79. is true; and M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſtill will averre, that all the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars of the ſtory from firſt to laſt hath nothing falſe in it. In that ſtory he tells you of a meeting concluded of upon the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Nicols</hi> his opinions, where I and M. <hi>Greenhill</hi> were; when as ſtill it is affirmed againe, and his onely witneſſe hee hath, acknowledges there was no ſuch meeting, neither I nor Maſter <hi>Greenhill</hi> never knew of ſuch a meeting. And he confeſſes that he did miſtake. If he ſhould find ſuch miſtakes in me, in his mouth they would be lyes. There is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing related, which ſurely is either true or falſe: but true it is not, for he confeſſes there was a miſtake, and yet he boldly ſayes that all the particulars of his relation are true, there is nothing falſe from firſt to laſt. What a man is this M. <hi>Edwards?</hi> he can relate a buſineſſe, he can miſtake in his relation, report that to be that never was, and yet all he ſayes is true. Caſt him where you will, he falls upon his legs.</p>
            <p>But he ſayes, there is onely a miſtake in the <hi>tranſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> He plainly relates two things. 1. <hi>Nicols</hi> his comming to M. <hi>Greenhil,</hi> venting ſuch opinions. 2. That upon that occaſion there was a meeting concluded of, where M. <hi>Greenhil</hi> and I he ſayes were; is this of a meeting, but a tranſition? Truly if Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> hath ſuch a liberty to make ſuch kind of tranſitions that ſhall make ſuch things to be that never were, he may by the help of his tranſitions tell and write lyes apace. Hereafter you muſt call M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his falſities, his tranſitions. Tranſition is a new figure M. <hi>Edwards</hi> hath invented; when you think he writes lies, it is becauſe of your dull capacity, not underſtanding his figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſpeaking; it is <hi>per Tranſitionem.</hi> By this he can heap up ſtory upon ſtory, and turne falſhoods into truths as he pleaſeth. This his Rhethorique raiſeth his Cretian art beyond what formerly it hath been.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:113727:6"/>
            <p>The Conteſt between me and M. <hi>Edwards</hi> in this thing is plainly this.</p>
            <p>I meet occaſionally with M. <hi>Greenhil;</hi> among many things in diſcourſe he expreſſes his great griefe at the horrid blaſphemies there are abroad; upon which I expreſſe likewiſe my ſenſe of ſuch things; and this is all M. <hi>Alle</hi> tells him: therefore I blame not the man ſo much as I blame M. <hi>Edwards</hi> for moulding reports as he pleaſeth, ſo as if he hath but a piece of a buſineſſe, he can make it up a whole buſineſſe as he thinks fit.</p>
            <p>After this paſſed between M. <hi>Greenhil</hi> and I, I find in a Booke M. <hi>Edwards</hi> relating a ſtory of one <hi>Nicols</hi> in Moore-fields, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing damnable opinions, a man I never had heard of in my life, and that upon occaſion of him, a meeting was concluded of, where he ſayes I was; which meeting I never had heard of, and it was ſtrange to me to find my ſelfe ſet downe in print, to be at ſuch a meeting, ſpeaking ſuch things, when I never heard of the man, nor of any meeting about him, nor of any of his opinions.</p>
            <p>But did I never ſay thoſe words upon no other occaſion menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his Book?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> If you ſhould aske me whether I have not ſaid words to that purpoſe twenty and twenty times, I could not deny it; but what is that to this buſineſſe? I put the caſe thus, Suppoſe a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter comming from the Weſt to London, had come to M. <hi>Bella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> ſhop to buy a Book, and there he ſhould heare ſome bemoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the damnable opinions that are vented in London, as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve hath been often there, and this Miniſter there expreſſing his diſlike, ſhould afterwards find in a Book that there is one <hi>Nicols</hi> in Moore-fields, a man whom he never had heard of, holding dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable opinions, and a meeting concluded of about what this <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cols</hi> had vented, at which he was ſaying thus and thus, ſomething to which effect perhaps he had ſometime ſpoken in M. <hi>Bellamies</hi> ſhop occaſionally, would this ſtory be a true one? would it be a lye, or an equivocation, to ſay this ſtory is falſe? Or</p>
            <p>Take it thus. Suppoſe M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſhould ſay in his Pulpit at Chriſts Church, that he was the Angel that was to poure the vial upon the ſunne, and afterward there ſhould be this ſtory written, that there was a meeting, where miſtreſſe <hi>Katherine Chidley</hi> and M. <hi>Edwards</hi> were, and at that time M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſhould
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113727:7"/>ſay, I am the Angel of God prophecyed of, who am to poure forth the vyal upon the ſunne; would M. <hi>Edwards</hi> think this ſtory were a true one? Surely a truer ſtory then that he hath in that page of his booke 79. in this regard that he had heard of ſuch an one as <hi>Katherine Chidley,</hi> I had never heard of ſuch an one as <hi>Nicols.</hi> If M. <hi>Edwards</hi> be reſolved to take this liberty, to raiſe, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, to make ſtories thus, what may he not ſay? He may eaſily fill bookes every moneth with ſtories enough, which he can put into what ſhape he pleaſeth, eſpecially conſidering how he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites all men to bring him what ſtories they can, with promiſe to conceale their names, crying in every ſtreet, <hi>Duſt, Duſt.</hi> No marvell his Cart is ſo full.</p>
            <p>After all this that is ſaid, were it much more to this or any thing elſe, it is eaſie for him to cry out in M. <hi>Bellamies</hi> ſhop, and afterwards in his Booke, <hi>It is a lye, it is a lye, nothing but jugling, nothing but Ieſuiticall equivocation. Oh what ſtrange men are theſe!</hi> But you know the man, and the manner of his communication.</p>
            <p>Page 94. of the ſecond part of his <hi>Gangraena,</hi> he enquires what the reaſons might be that <hi>M. Burroughes</hi> and <hi>M. Greenhil</hi> ſhould conſpire together to give ſuch a teſtimony in writing. But whence doth it appeare that <hi>M. Greenhill</hi> gave this teſtimony in writing? his hand is not to it. How doth it appeare that hee conſpired it ſhould be given in writing? may not I relate what he ſaid, and yet he not conſpire to give it in writing? That wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting I take wholly upon my ſelfe. He gives three reaſons why he thinks we did it: The firſt two are from his being conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of evill in himſelfe and Booke: His third is, that they might free themſelves from ſuſpition of being againſt a toleration of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſects and opinions.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Why man, is there more in what is related here, then I have preached and publiſhed in print? why ſhould I then be afraid to have ſuch expreſſions knowne? And page 98. <hi>M. Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> ſayes that this meeting was a little before <hi>M. Burroughes</hi> fell upon the preaching of the power of the magiſtrate in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, and point of Toleration; and was it ſo? Surely then <hi>M. Burroughes</hi> was not ſo afraid of ſuſpition to be for the repreſſing ſuch horrible things as <hi>M. Edwards</hi> would ſeeme to make him; he that preached and printed what <hi>Burroughes</hi> did,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113727:7"/>would not be afraid to owne his being againſt ſuch horrid opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons as much as maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> his relation from maſter <hi>Alle</hi> comes to.</p>
            <p>He falls foulely upon me in page 92. of the firſt part of his <hi>Gangraena,</hi> as a double minded man; of all the Apologiſts he ſayes I ſometimes ſeeme to come neere, and then I fly off againe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> I doe profeſſe my endeavours have been what I could to come neere my brethren whom I honour, and I account it an af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction to me that the diſtance is ſo great, I have laboured to make it as little as may be, I have ſhewne my ſelfe willing to goe to the uttermoſt line, yea <hi>punctum</hi> I have ſeene truth in; and this I have obſerved in ſome, they have been angry when they have ſeen their brethren come neere them, becauſe then they could not get ſo full a blow at them as when they were at a farther diſtance.</p>
            <p>No, you will ſay, we are not angry that you come ſo neere, but that you goe back againe from what you ſeemed to come neere in.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> If any man living can ſhew in any one thing wherein I have gone back from what I appeared to be neare, either in any thing I have done in the Aſſembly, in preaching, or confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, I will fall downe at his feet, and beare my ſhame: I one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly except M. <hi>Edwards</hi> from being my Judge: The accuſations or condemnations of a ſhameleſſe man ſhall never make me aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Upon the moſt diligent ſearch I could make into my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, I doe not know that in any particle wherein I have come neare my bretheren of the Presbyteriall judgment in the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly or otherwiſe, that ever I ſtarted back in the leaſt; yea let any bring forth what ever I have ſaid in the Aſſembly, either formerly or lately, what ever I have delivered in preaching, printing, or conferring, wherein they thinke I came neareſt my Brethren, I hereby profeſſe that I am ſtill the ſame, and that I will upon any occaſion publiſh my ſelfe to be the ſame. Indeed of all the Apologiſts, Providence put me upon that work of handling the point of <hi>Heart-Diviſions,</hi> and I bleſſe God I did it in the uprightneſſe of my heart. In that argument I was put upon ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how neare men called Independents came to thoſe of the Presbyterian judgement, wherein I declared my ſelfe freely. Now
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113727:8"/>let not M. <hi>Edwards</hi> be angry with me for going along with him two miles, becauſe I cannot goe three; and becauſe he thinks if I yeeld thus farre, I cannot but contradict the whole cauſe, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept I will contradict my former aſſertions: Let him not be diſpleaſed with me, though I be not of his mind; his bluſtring ſpirit may make my ſpeeches or lines ſeeme to lye croſſe, but let a meek, quiet ſpirited man look on them, and they will lye right enough, as they have done to many Presbyteriall Brethren. Although nothing under heaven would more rejoyce me then to help to find out any expedient whereby I might agree with my Brethren who are for the Claſſicall and Provinciall Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, yet I muſt needs profeſſe that all that I have hitherto heard in the Aſſembly or elſewhere, after (I hope) ſincere labouring with my heart and with God, that <hi>I</hi> might know his truth, hath not ſhaken nor cauſed any Scruple in thoſe Principles my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience hath beene engaged in, againſt the extending that ruling power of Paſtors and Teachers our Brethren challenge beyond their charge of feeding by the Word and Sacraments.</p>
            <p>And though I be in Mr. <hi>Edwards</hi> his thoughts the worſt of all the Apologiſts when I am againſt him, which I dare not gaineſay, yet when I doe any thing that pleaſes him, then he calls me a chiefe man among the diſſenting Brethren, as <hi>pag.</hi> 212. of his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of his <hi>Gangraena,</hi> where he cites my ſpeech lately prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, made in Guildhall for the Scots. By which ſpeech, Mr. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> and all men may ſee, that difference in judgement hinders not me from giving that honour to men that God would have given them, neither takes it off my heart from them. But am I of the ſame minde ſtill?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Whatſoever change there may be, yet the difference of our judgements in point of Presbytery makes not the change, for I then apprehended them at as great a diſtance from me in that, as now I doe. But ſtill I doe, and cannot but as long as I live ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them, and bleſſe God for them, as the great inſtruments of the firſt turne of the ſtreame of oppreſſion and Tyrannie; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever becomes of me, I have learned to honour thoſe whom God honours: Let me have the ſame principles that then I went upon, which in me are not changed; I could make ſuch another ſpeech for them.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:113727:8"/>
            <p>What ſhould I follow this vaine man in any farther particulars? both in his laſt, and in his former books, he vents a very angry ſpirit againſt me, though never provoked by me, which I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wondered at; why man! what is the matter? what have I done? what comes it to more then the old non-conformiſts not communicating with the Churches here, becauſe they could not joyne in kneeling? their ſcruple lay in one thing, mine in another. But though many of our Brethren thought, and I beleeve ſtill doe thinke they were in an error, yet their ſpirits were calme and quiet towards them. What is it that raiſes the wind againſt me and others, (ſuppoſe we be in an error) except it be the hope that theſe men have of having power in their owne hands, which formerly they had not? I have hitherto abſtained from that which is moſt provoking. What have I then done that thus angers the man? He is diſpleaſed that I preach ſo much, that I have ſo many Lectures. I will not tell of the Livings, preferments, Sequeſtrations, Lectures, that thoſe of the Presbyteriall judgement have. What would he have mee lay downe a Lecture, and gather a Church? This would anger him more. Though I ſought none of thoſe I have, yet <hi>I</hi> was not unwilling to yeeld to Gods call in the deſires of the people, ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch a doore of ſervice, though the continuance of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the work was like to be beyond my ſtrength, becauſe (to ſpeak plainly) <hi>I</hi> ſaw ſuch a ſpirit working, that I feared the door for my preaching would ere long be ſhut, this made me to caſt my ſelfe upon God for ſtrength to doe as much work as poſſibly I could in the time when opportunity was continued; and <hi>I</hi> could tell ſad ſtories that would make others think as <hi>I</hi> did. He is troubled at the Meanes I have, though it be much leſſe then he mentions, and as at great an uncertainty as may be; if men be taxed for any thing more then they like, they know where to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve themſelves in withdrawing from ſuch contributions; if any weakneſſe of body hinders the continuance in the greatneſſe of the labour, the meanes preſently ceaſes; yet I have no reaſon to complaine. But this I ſay, if ever I grow rich by commings in for preaching, let me lye under cenſures as abſurd as M. <hi>Edwards</hi> himſelfe can deviſe.</p>
            <p>But it may be he is angry with me becauſe though my practice
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113727:9"/>offends him not ſo much as others, yet I countenance and plead for thoſe whom he cryes out againſt as Schiſmatiques.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> I profeſſe, as in the preſence of God, that upon the moſt ſerious examination of my heart, I find in it, that were my judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Presbyteriall, yet I ſhould preach and plead as much for the forbearance of Brethren differing from me, not onely in their judgement, but in their practice, as I have ever done; therefore if I ſhould turne a Presbyterian, I feare I ſhould trouble M. <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> and ſome others more then now I doe; perhaps my pleading and preaching for forbearance of diſſenting Brethren would be of more force then now it is.</p>
            <p>He and others make a great out-cry againſt Schiſme, they think and ſay that men leaving a true Church, cannot be freed from the charge of Schiſme.</p>
            <p>To that I would onely ſay thus much, Suppoſe the Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, or thoſe of the Scottiſh Nation, who lived in the City in former times, who could not acknowledge the Biſhops authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor communicate in the Sacraments in the pariſhes where they lived without ſinne to them, ſtill acknowledging them to be true Churches, yet if the Parliament had made an Act where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they ſhould have had two or three places in the City appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them, wherein all that could not conforme to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline then eſtabliſhed, ſhould have had liberty to have had the Sacraments and other Church-Ordinances together in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by themſelves, freed from the burden of Ceremonies, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to Epiſcopall Authority, would they not have bleſſed God for this liberty, had they been Schiſmatiques, in the enjoyment of this liberty? Certainly the allowance of the State will not alter the caſe; if it be Schiſme to doe thus without allowance of the State, and venturing upon ſuffering, it is Schiſme when the State does allow it, when they are freed from ſuffering, Schiſme is a Church ſinne. What ever offence againſt Order of State men may be charged with, who gather thus without allowance of the State, yet they are not therefore Schiſmatiques, becauſe they doe that without the allowance of the State, which if the State did allow of, would not be Schiſme: where the Lutherans &amp; Calviniſts have liberty to live in one Country together, and yet not communicating one with another; are all the Lutherans, or
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:113727:9"/>all the Calviniſts, Schiſmaticks? Suppoſe the Greek Churches had liberty to live among us, would they be all Schiſmaticks to us, or ſhould we be ſo to them? Many of the French and Dutch Churches who live in our pariſhes, though they underſtand our language well enough, yet would not communicate in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes where they live, becauſe of the Ceremonies and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to Biſhops, were they all Schiſmaticks too? Doe not men ordinarily in London and elſewhere for the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward advantage of trade or otherwiſe, leave one Church and goe to another? and may not a man for any advantage of enjoyment of Ordinances that he cannot have in the Church he formerly li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in, not in that purity, but that it will be ſinne in him to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue in it, remove to another Church? and what if his dwelling be not removed to the other ſide of the ſtreet, does that make it Schiſme? Many of the converted Jewes were a great while in Church-Communion before they ſaw their liberty to converſe with the Gentiles, though converted alſo: it was their fault that they would not joyne with the Gentiles being Chriſtians, the partition wall being broken downe, yet they were never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Schiſmatiques for this fault of theirs; whereas now if a man lives in a pariſh, and does not joyn in Church fellowſhip in that pariſh, he is branded for a Schiſmatique. What hurt the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of words, and among others this of Schiſme hath done in the Church, we all know. When men who give good teſtimony of their godlineſſe and peaceableneſſe, after all meanes uſed in faithfulneſſe to know the mind of Chriſt, they cannot without ſin to them (though it be through weakneſſe) enjoy all the ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt, and partake in all the duties of Worſhip as members of that Congregation where their dwelling is, they therefore in all humility and meekneſſe deſire they may not live without the ordinances of Chriſt all their dayes, but for the enjoyment of them may joyne in another Congregation, yet ſo as not condemning thoſe Churches they joyne not with, as falſe, but ſtill preſerve all Chriſtian communion with the Saints, as members of the ſame body of Chriſt, of the Church Catholique, and joyn alſo with them in all duties of worſhip that belong to particular Churches, ſo far as they are able. If this be called Schiſme, it is more then yet I have learned, or then (I beleeve) M. <hi>Edwards</hi> can teach me.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:113727:10"/>
            <p>Page 98. he throwes me his glove, challenging me into the field to try his valour with me in this point.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> When I have a mind to play at Brawle and Wrangle, I will take up his glove. He hath given an experiment of his wrangling faculty in the maintenance of the charge he gives me of being guilty of the 150. Error, mentioned in the firſt part of his <hi>Gangraena,</hi> namely, <hi>Whatſoever errors or miſcarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges in Religion the Church ſhould beare withall in men conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuing them ſtill in communion with them, theſe the Magiſtrate ſhould beare with, continuing them in the Kingdome or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, in the enjoyment of the liberty of ſubjects,</hi> this with M. <hi>Edwards</hi> is a huge error: Whereas he paſſes almoſt all his other errors without any animadverſion, he muſt needs have one here, he cannot paſſe ſo foule an error as this without confuting it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, ſee what his Confutation is: Thoſe (ſayes he) who out of conſcience are not ſatisfyed in taking up Armes againſt Armies raiſed by a Prince, the Church will not deale with for this, but the Magiſtrate may. To this M. <hi>John Goodwin</hi> anſwered, that I before had ſaid that in matters of civil juſtice between man and man, there the plea of conſcience would not free a man from puniſh-went if he offends; but for matters of Religion, there what ever charge the Magiſtrate hath over men, it is not more then the charge the Church hath in its kind; therefore where the Church ſhould beare with men, the Magiſtrate ſhould. Now the man comes in with his refutation and inſtances in a buſineſſe of taking up Armes, as if this did not come under the Head ſpoken of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, namely, the matters of civil juſtice, not a matter of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as diſtinct from civil juſtice: and his Reply is onely this, as if an erroneous conſcience did not make things the Magiſtrate ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts matters of State, matters of Religion, and the Magiſtrate alſo reckon many things to be matters of State, which many conſciences account high matters in Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> What a bable is this? who would ſpend his time in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to it? If M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his valour in diſpute may be jud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by this, we need never feare encountring with him. I ſay that in matters of Religion as diſtinct from matters of civil juſtice, there the Magiſtrates power extends not beyond the Churches: and he comes and tells us that an erroneous conſcience may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113727:10"/>matters of State, matters of Religion, what then? if he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts them to be matters of Religion, does this alter the nature of the thing? what ever he accounts, yet if he does offend againſt civill juſtice, he is to be puniſhed; and whatſoever the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate accounts, yet if the thing in its owne nature be not againſt civill juſtice, but onely againſt ſome rule of Religion, ſurely he is not to puniſh in his way, further then the Church may in her way; who ſpeaks of what one man accounts, or what another man accounts, the things muſt be judged according to what they are in their owne nature: if M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his threatning Peece doe no better feats then his Animadverſion and Reply to M. <hi>John Goodwin</hi> hath done, that which he judges an Error remaines ſtill a Truth, he muſt blot it out of his Catalogue of Errors, his conſcience muſt tell him there is one Error leſſe then his recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: but I would be loth to be writing or waiting till Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> his conſcience be convinced, or if it be, till he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes it to be.</p>
            <p>There is onely one paſſage more that I ſhall need to take notice of in his laſt Book, and ſomething he hath of it in his former, namely, my conformity in the Biſhops times. This conformity he ſpeaks of was ten yeeres ſince, and though I did conforme to ſome of the old Ceremonies, in which I acknowledge my ſinne; I doe not caſt thoſe things off as inconvenient or diſcountenanced by the State onely, but as ſinfull againſt Chriſt; yet I think there can hardly be found any Man in that Dioceſſe where I was, who was ſo eyed as I was, that did conforme leſſe then I did, if he conformed at all. As for the new conformity, God kept me from it; and my ſinne in the old, makes me to be of the more forbearing ſpirit towards thoſe who now differ from me. I ſee now what I did not; and I bleſſe God I ſaw it before the times changed: and others, even ſome who ſcorne at new light, muſt acknowledge they ſee now what a while ſince they ſaw not; why then ſhould they or I fly upon our Brethren, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſee not what we think we ſee? Oh how unbeſeeming is it for ſuch who conformed to old and new Ceremonies, now to be harſh and bitter in the leaſt degree againſt their Brethren, who differ from them, when they doe differ ſo much from what they were themſelves but a while ſince I ſome of them know I
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113727:11"/>loved them as Brethren, when they conformed to that I could not, but was ſuſpended for denying it. Let me have the ſame love from them as Brethren, though I cannot now conforme to all they now doe. True! where ſinnes are repented of, they are to be buryed, but ſo as ſinners be willing to lye downe in their ſhame, and walke beſeeming their repentance for ſuch ſinnes.</p>
            <p>Thus have I ſpent time about this boiſterous, froward ſpirited man, which I grudge as much as ever I grudged any time ſince I knew what the worth of time was: But yet ſeeing my pen is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it ſhall paſſe upon what this man hath in that angry <hi>Antia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologia</hi> in reference to my ſelfe. He hath two things againſt me: 1. My going out of the Kingdome: 2 My Preaching and Writing for the Congregationall way. For the firſt he ſayes, pag. 19. <hi>That M.</hi> Burroughes <hi>for ſome ſpeeches ſpoken againſt the Scottiſh Warre, in ſome company not to be truſted, he for feare fled in all haſte to Rotterdam.</hi> This he mentions in divers places of his Book. He ſayes, this made him ſtumble at the truth of ſome things before mentioned in the Apologie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> He willingly layes this ſtumbling block before himſelfe. Had he been willing to have conferred with me about this as I deſired, before he printed, I ſhould have ſo fully ſatisfied him about my going out of the Kingdome, that he could never have ſtumbled at this, not have cauſed others to ſtumble as he hath done.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he ſayes, ſome ſpeeches were ſpoke, for feare whereof I, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>How does he know there were ſpeeches ſpoke, for fear where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I fled? It may be there was onely an accuſation of ſpeeches, for feare whereof, &amp;c. In his bold Aſſertion there is held forth to the world at leaſt ſome indiſcretion in me, that I ſhould ſpeak words of a high nature in company not to be truſted. But in that buſineſſe I am ſo fully cleare, as I wiped off before my Lord of <hi>Warwick</hi> whatſoever might have ſeemed indiſcretion, not by mine owne Aſſertion onely, but by the teſtimony of two Gentlemen, all the company beſides the Accuſer, who were preſent at the whole diſcourſe of that matter. The truth is, there were no ſuch ſpeeches that I ſpake, for feare whereof I
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113727:11"/>haſted away, there was onely ſome accuſation of ſpeeches, and <hi>Si ſat ſit accuſaſſe, quis innocens erit?</hi> What man can free him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from Accuſation?</p>
            <p>Secondly, He ſaies in all haſt I fled to <hi>Rotterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> It was foure or five months after this accuſation before I went to <hi>Rotterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Had not the Prelatical faction been incenſed againſt me for ſtanding out againſt their ſuperſtitions, I ſhould have ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured to have ſtood to what I ſpake, for all I ſaid was but by way Quaere, affirming nothing, for I knew how dangerous the times were then, but putting quarrels tending to juſtifie the Scots when they firſt roſe in Armes, hearing them rayled on in the company where I was, all my danger was in ſtanding for them, and that with that warineſſe that ſuch times required. But I knew what the power of the Prelaticall party at that time was, who were extreamly incenſed againſt me; a mans innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy then, could not be his ſafety: I being moſt foulely traduced in the report of my words, though the two other Gentlemen clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red me never ſo much, as my Lord of <hi>Warwick</hi> knowes, (for the Conference was in his Garden) yet one witneſſe affirmative in ſuch a caſe would have been taken againſt an hundred negatives. A meere Accuſation then was enough to cauſe me to provide for my ſecurity.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, but ſuppoſe before any ſuch Accuſation and danger, when I was in peace and ſafety, that then I had my call to the Clutch of <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> yea and had entertained this call, and acknowledged God much in it, (as indeed I had cauſe) and that this came but as an after Providence of God to make my way more cleare to me, and to take off fully all my friends, from whom it would have been hard without ſome ſuch providence to have got off, without much trouble. Will it not appeare that M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ventures boldly to relate whatſoever he heares, and to put what conſtructions upon it he pleaſes, for he brings in this ſtory to prove me falſe, in the ſaying with the reſt of the Apologiſts, that <hi>we ſaw the evil of thoſe ſuperſtitions that were adjoyned to the Worſhip of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The true ſtory of this buſineſſe is this, which ſeeing Providence calls it forth, I hope God may have glory by it.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:113727:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I being by Biſhop <hi>Wren,</hi> deprived of my living in <hi>Norfolke,</hi> In which I believe I endured as great a brunt, as almoſt any of thoſe which ſtayed in <hi>England;</hi> though M. <hi>Edwards</hi> is pleaſed to ſay <hi>Page</hi> 19. of his <hi>Antiapologie,</hi> that we fled, that we might be ſafe upon the Shore, while our Bretheren were at ſea in the Storm. I believe neither he, nor ſcarce any of our <hi>Presbyteriall Brethren,</hi> endured a harder Storm at Sea, then I did before I went out of <hi>England;</hi> Yet I bleſſe God, he ſtirred up noble friends to countenance and encourage me in my ſufferings: For which I will not ceaſe to pray that the bleſſing of God may be upon them and their Families. I for ſome Months living with my L<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: of <hi>Warwick,</hi> with whom I found much undeſerved love and reſpect, when I was in the midſt of as great encouragements for ſtaying in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as a man deprived, and under the Biſhops rage, could expect, I ſet my ſelf in as ſerious a manner as ever I remember I did in all my life, to examine my heart about my ſtaying in <hi>England,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſome carnall reſpects, that countenance I had from diverſe noble friends, the offers of Livings, did not begin to prevaile too farre with me; my ſpirit was much troubled with theſe thoughts, Why do I ſtill linger in <hi>England,</hi> where I cannot with peace en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy what my ſoule longes after? Did I not formerly thinke, that if ever God tooke me clearly from my People, I would haſten to be where I might be free from ſuch mixtures in Gods worſhip, without wringing my conſcience any more? Why do I therefore now ſtay? Am I not under a temptation? God knowes theſe were the ſad and ſerious workings of my ſpirit, and the workings of my heart were as ſtrong, as ever I felt them in my life; Now whilſt I was thus muſing, thus troubled in my ſpirit, and lifting my heart up to God to helpe me, and ſet me at liberty, leaning upon my Chamber window, I eſpyed a man in a Citizens habit, coming in the Court Yard towards my Chamber, and in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming near, I knew him to be formerly a Citizen of <hi>Norwich,</hi> but at that time, one of the Church of <hi>Rotterdam;</hi> this man comes to me, and tels me that he came lately from <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> that he was ſent by the Chrurch there, to give me a call, to joyn with M. <hi>Bridge</hi> in the worke of the Lord, in that Church; when I heard him ſay thus, I ſtood a while amazed at the providence of God, that at ſuch a time a Meſſenger ſhould be ſent to me about ſuch an errand; my
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:113727:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>heart God knowes exceedingly rejoyced in this call of his, I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently told him I ſaw. God much in it, and dared not in the leaſt to gainſay it, yea, that my heart did much cloſe with it, yet deſired to ſee God a little further in it, this only I required, that he ſhould go or ſend to the Church and return my anſwer: with deſire, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe moſt of them knew me, they ſhould give me their call under their own bands, and then there would be nothing wanting that I knew, but I was theirs, and thus we parted. In this my heart was much eaſed, now ſeeing a cleare hand of God taking me off from temptations, that I was affraid might otherwiſe have ſtucke upon me, but this I kept to my ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Now as God would have it, three or foure dayes after this, a friend meets me, and tels me, that ſuch a man reported of me, that in a conference about the <hi>Scots,</hi> juſtifying them in what they did, I ſhould ſpeake ſuch things as might bring me into trouble; After I heard this, I could not but take notice of Gods hand, that ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now God intended to open the dore very wide, for that call I had to <hi>Rotterdam;</hi> yet becauſe, whether I went out or ſtayed in the Land, I deſired to cleare my ſelfe as much as could be; I went to this accuſer with one of the Gentlemen, who was at our whole diſcourſe, we both laboured to convince him that he had miſtook what was ſaid in that Conference, that certainly there was no ſuch thing as he had reported, though at firſt there appeared a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry evill ſpirit in him, as if he intended evill againſt me, yet I went freely up and downe for a fortnight or three weeks after in the Countrey, and got another Gentleman, who alſo heard all that Conference, to ſpeak with him; at the laſt he began to recant of what he had ſaid, and promiſed to me and one of the Gentlemen who had heard all our former diſcourſe, that he would take me off what he could, that he would ſatisfie all that he had told any thing againſt me unto, and now tell them that he was miſtaken in me, and that things were not ſo bad as he apprehended, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſaid he made no doubt but to ſet me right againe. After this I hoped all would blow over, my Lord of <hi>Warwick</hi> falling ſick at <hi>London,</hi> ſent for me, I came up to him, continuing with him a fortnight or three weeks longer, going freely up and downe the City, my Lord knew all the buſineſſe, and made no queſtion but all was over. Now I being as I hoped ſet free from my Accuſer,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:113727:13"/>the Meſſenger from <hi>Rotterdam</hi> comes to me againe, with an anſwer to what I had deſired, ſhewing me how the Church there had met, and had ſent a call to me in writing under the Elders hands, with many other hands in the name of the Church: upon which we agreed upon the day when, and the place where we ſhould meet in <hi>Norfolke,</hi> to make a full concluſion, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly to take order for our voyage. Now within three or foure dayes after this ſecond call, this buſineſſe that we thought had been dead, breaks forth againe afreſh: I had intelligence from a Miniſter in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> that the truth was, he that accuſed me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, had dealt treacherouſly with me, and the buſineſſe grew to a height, it was come to the then Lord Treaſurer: Upon this ſtill I ſaw my call the clearer and fuller, and at my fore-appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed time went into <hi>Norfolke,</hi> where I met with the Meſſenger, and concluded the going into <hi>Holland.</hi> Though my call by this was clearer, yet the thought of going out of the Kingdome thus, was grievous to me, for I knew I muſt never ſee <hi>England</hi> againe, times continuing as then they were, and no man living could have imagined that alteration that after fell out.</p>
            <p>Now I appeale to M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> had he knowne all this (which if it had pleaſed him he might have done, for I ſent to him to tell him I would ſatisfie him about this buſineſſ) would he have made ſuch a relation as he hath done, to ſuch a purpoſe as he hath done? for of all the things he hath againſt me, the manner of my going out of the Kingdome in the way that he relates it, is the greateſt aſperſion that is upon me, when indeed it was one of the moſt mercifull providences of God to me that ever befell me in all my life, wherein I ſaw as cleerly an eye of God watching over me in particular for good, as ever in any thing. <hi>I</hi> know not what a bold daring ſpirit, whoſe aims are to aſperſe men, would have done in this caſe, had this <hi>I</hi> now relate been knowne, as it was to many; but ingenuity certainly, where it had been in the leaſt degree of it, would have abhorred to have done as M. <hi>Edwards</hi> hath done. The Lord ſet his conſcience upon him, rebuke him, and be mercifull to him in this thing.</p>
            <p>His ſecond thing he hath againſt me in his <hi>Antiapologia,</hi> is his Charge for my Preaching for the Congregationall way, as page 216. he ſayes <hi>I</hi> preached at <hi>Mildreds</hi> Breadſtreet, <hi>againſt Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:113727:13"/>Churches under the New Teſtament, and for the way of their particular Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> But what I ſaid for that way, he mentions not, and I remember not, therefore I can ſay nothing to it; but concerning a Nationall Church, <hi>I</hi> doe remember <hi>I</hi> ſaid ſomething, it was in the time of the Prelates, my ſpeech was directed againſt them, it was the day the firſt Proteſtation was taken, becauſe a great argument they uſe for their power over Nations, is from the power of the High Prieſt over the whole Nation of the Jewes. I ſaid that we were freed from the Paedagogie of the Jewes, and now there were no Nationall Churches by inſtitution as the Jewes were, mentioning theſe 3. things. 1. There are no natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Officers as they had. 2. No Nationall Worſhip as they had. 3. It was not ſufficient now, to make a member of the Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe one is by birth of this or any other Nation, as then it was, becauſe one was borne of the Nation of the Jewes. And is this a Doctrine that will not goe downe with a Presbyterian? Surely it muſt be a Prelaticall Presbyterian who cannot digeſt this; I am confident all the Presbyterian Churches in the World will acknowledge what I ſaid here to be true. That we may call the Church in England a Nationall Church becauſe of the many Saints in it who are of the body of Chriſt, I deny not, nor ever did, but that it is by the inſtitution of Chriſt formed into one po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall Church as the Nation of the Jewes was, this is no Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency to deny; where are any particular men ſtanding Church Officers to the whole Nation by Divine inſtitution? what Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall worſhip hath Chriſt inſtituted? doth our Birth in the Nation make us members of the Church? Theſe things are ſo palpably plaine to any that will underſtand, that it is tedious to ſpend time about them.</p>
            <p>He ſayes further in the ſame page, that I preaching before the Lord Major and Aldermen, preached for a Toleration of all Sects and Opinions, ſo they were not againſt Fundamentals in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and Fundamentals in Civil Government.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Then I did not preach for an univerſall, an unlimited toleration of all Religions, of all things, as both my ſelfe and others are very ſinfully reported to doe. What was the way of getting hands to a late Petition in London but this, when ſome
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:113727:14"/>went from houſe to houſe, <hi>Who are you for? Are you for Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, or Independencie?</hi> Many anſwering, <hi>They knew not what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependencie was;</hi> The Hand-gatherers replyed, <hi>Independents are ſuch as would have no Government, as would have all Religions, all Blaſphemiss and Hereſies tolerated, as would live under no Laws: Oh,</hi> ſay they, <hi>No, we are not for them, we will ſet our hands againſt them,</hi> and thus hands might eaſily multiply. Yea this is the weapon by which Miniſters in their Pulpits, where no body can anſwer them, fight againſt Independency with. But is this faire? Doe not your conſciences condemne you in this thing? For my part, as I never was, ſo I now am not for a toleration of all things, nay I ſhould be loth to live in <hi>England</hi> if ever it ſhould be here. I doe and ſhall pray and endeavour againſt it. But what I ſaid before the Lord Major and the Aldermen, had I been a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian I ſhould have ſaid it, and were I a Presbyterian I ſhould ſay it againe. The Presbyteriall way had once need of ſuch a doctrine, and may have need of it againe. I remember not the words that then I ſpoke, but this I remember, what I ſaid was from the 14. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> and I am ſure I have ſince ſaid and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in that Treatiſe of <hi>Heart-Diviſions</hi> three times as much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that Argument, and that Scripture, and yet I beleeve many hundreds of Presbyterians think what I have publiſhed there to be true doctrine, onely M. <hi>Edwards</hi> has ſo much of the Prelacy and violence in him, that he cannot digeſt it.</p>
            <p>As for my Lectures that are printed upon <hi>Heſea,</hi> that he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions page 220. I am not willing to ſpend time in anſwering, he mentions no particular words, but refers you to the Lectures and pages. They are to be ſeene, I refer my ſelfe to all moderate Presbyterians, let them judge whether there be any thing there that may not ſtand with Presbyterian Principles. Never any have appeared againſt thoſe Lectures but M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> and lately M. <hi>John Vicars;</hi> I reverence, and teach others to reverence old age; but it muſt know there are many infirmities attending it, it is fitter for devotion, then that it ſhould intereſt it ſelfe in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of contention. If M. <hi>Vicars</hi> had told me ſome experiences of the work of God upon his ſoule, or of the good providences of God towards his people and himſelfe in the courſe of his life, I ſhould have diligently obſerved them, and I hope might have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:113727:14"/>got good by them; But oh how unbecomming old age is that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of contention that appeares in his Bookes! if he thinks thoſe places he has cited will ſerve his turne, ſurely his skill in Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie is not great, my pen was running in a hard expreſſion, but I will not provoke the old man: yet I muſt be plaine with him, How uncomely is it for an old Profeſſor of Piety and Religion, to be found jeering and ſcorning at Piety and Religion? who would have thought that ever M. <hi>Vicars</hi> ſhould have lived to that day? Thus he does in the Frontiſpice of his Booke, <hi>The names of the five pious Apologiſts, and the names of the ſeven Religious Remonſtrants.</hi> Whereas the chiefe ſcope of his Book is to caſt dirt upon theſe Apologiſts and Remonſtrants. Certainly the ſpirit of the man is much altered from what he heretofore ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be. Can it become the gravity and wiſdome of old age to charge (and that publiquely) his Brethren of unworthy double dealing, of unfaithfulneſſe, upon no other ground then the relation of one man, and that relation but upon one witneſſe? and yet this very witneſſe gives it under his hand, that what theſe men that he charges thus, hath ſaid is true, and why muſt he charge Maſter <hi>Greenhill</hi> too? Surely he did not thinke what he did, for all that M. <hi>Greenhill</hi> ſaid, was, he wondred to ſee ſuch a thing in Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> his Booke, as a Relation of a meeting concluded of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Nicols,</hi> where I and he (M. <hi>Edwards</hi> ſayes) were; what doubleneſſe or unfaithfulneſſe in this? for not onely M. <hi>Edwards</hi> his witneſſe ſayes he never told him ſo, and ſuch a thing never was, but M. <hi>Edwards</hi> now confeſſes it. Is there then weight e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for ſuch a charge of M. <hi>Vicars,</hi> not onely upon me, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on M. <hi>Greenhil?</hi> The Lord, I hope, will cauſe M. <hi>Vicars</hi> to ſee cauſe to be humbled for this.</p>
            <p>In the cloſe of all me thinkes I ſee M. <hi>Edwards</hi> in M. <hi>Bellamies</hi> ſhop fretting and vaporing, I will anſwer him, I that I will, I will reply, I that I will: like one <hi>Piſe, Jerome</hi> ſpeaks of, who though he knew not what to ſay, yet he knew not how to hold his peace. M. <hi>Edwards</hi> may be bold enough in Anſwering, for I am perſwaded he beleeves I will hardly ever be brought to trouble my ſelf about him; He is ſo foule, who can meddle with him without dirtying his fingers? I am reſolved rather to lye under many prejudices and cenſures, and commit my name and cauſe to God, then to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:113727:15"/>trouble my ſelfe further with him. Though I will not fully conclude never to doe any thing further about him in publique, yet this I engage my ſelfe unto, that if any thing in what he has ſaid, or ſhall ſay, ſhall ſtick in the hearts of any conſcientious, who deſire ſatisfaction, if they will but make it knowne to any that have or ever had any acquaintance with me, I will (if it be deſired) give them ſatisfaction in it; but I confeſſe I am loth to promiſe this to ſtrangers, I have been ſo traduced by ſtrangers who have come to me for ſatisfaction in ſome caſes of conſcience. For inſtance, in that about a late Petition of ſome of the Citizens, which M. <hi>Edwards</hi> mentions <hi>page</hi> 110. of the firſt part of his <hi>Gangraena,</hi> where he ſayes, ſome came to me the day after I preached, to be ſatisfied about it, who (he ſayes) put me hard to it. I confeſſe I ſpent neere foure houres with one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany who came to me about it; yet Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> ſayes, I ſaid little. It may be ſome of them reported ſo. How eaſie is it for any to come to be reſolved in a caſe of conſcience, and when they are gone, to ſay, He ſaid little? Yet to thoſe four who then came to me, there was ſo much ſaid, that two of them went away ſatisfied, and the other two fell off contradicting one another: The one ſaying, If there were that in the Petition that I objected, he would have no hand in it; the other of them ſaid to his friend, Certainly there is that in it. And after that, onely one company more came, that I remember, where one, an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Presbyterian, a great friend to M. <hi>Edwards,</hi> went away ſo ſatisfied, as he after profeſſed he never received more ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in any thing he had ſcrupled, and that with theſe reaſons I gave him he had ſatisfied two Miniſters, who before were of another mind; and yet it ſeems ſome were pleaſed to tell Maſter <hi>Edwards</hi> I ſaid little: it was eaſie for them to ſay ſo when they were gone, and themſelves muſt be the Judges of what I ſaid, and of what I affirmed. I refuſed none that came to me, but if I were at home, ſpake with, and debated the matter at large: I was abroad onely when one company came, of which I after had any notice, which was at the time of the Aſſembly, where I was; yet my wife earneſtly deſired them to come in the after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, and told them I ſhould very willingly confer with them: and two of that company did come, with whom I conferred at
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:113727:15"/>large, neere foure houres, although M. <hi>Edwards</hi> is pleaſed to ſay I ſpake little, but my wife much: whereas my ſpeech was not onely ſo long, but had that influence upon two of them, as is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned; and I remember not that my wife was with them, or made any ſtay, but after ſo much time ſpent, as ſhee thought it was time to break off, ſhe brought them a cup of beere, and ſtaid while they were drinking, or very little more. But can any man think but it muſt be very tedious for a man who hath any thing to doe, to ſpend time in anſwering ſuch bables as theſe? and yet becauſe even theſe bables take with vaine ſpirits, who willingly catch at every thing, ſomething muſt be ſaid, if it be but to pleaſe children.</p>
            <p>Thus have I wearyed my ſelfe, and it may be the Reader, in theſe perſonall things: of all books, I never cared to read books of this nature. The Lord deliver me from ſuch an implacable, fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious ſpirit as this M. <hi>Edwards</hi> hath, that I may have no more to doe with him. If he pretends at any time to deale in a rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall way, he mingles ſuch perſonall things, as muſt needs make it tedious for any man of ingenuity, who hath any thing of weight to take up his head or heart, to meddle with him. Let any man write a rationall diſcourſe, acknowledged by themſelves to have much ſtrength in it, againſt that way ſo much oppoſed, and then let them complaine if they have no Anſwer. Some few things have been publiſhed this way, and moſt of them have had Anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, and when God gives further liberty from other occaſions, further Anſwer ſhall appeare in publique. But is it poſſible for ſo few of us, having ſo many things lye upon us, to attend the Anſwer to every Pamphlet that comes out againſt us?</p>
            <p>That extreme eagerneſſe and violence in Maſter <hi>Edwards,</hi> M. <hi>Vicars,</hi> and others, to aſperſe our names, makes us to think that God hath made more uſe of our names then we were aware of, and ſhall be an argument to quicken us to more watchfulneſſe to walk inoffenſively and convincingly before all men. For we ſee by their anger, even almoſt to madneſſe bent that way, that they had little hope to prevaile with all their arguments againſt the cauſe wee profeſſe, till they could get downe our eſteeme (ſuch as it was) in the hearts of the people. The old way of the Heathens againſt the Chriſtians in the Primitive
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:113727:16"/>times, and of the Prelates againſt the Presbyterians when time was. But our names are not in the power of their tongues and pens, they are in the hands of God, who will preſerve them ſo farre as he hath uſe of them, and further we ſhall have no uſe of them our ſelves.</p>
            <p>There is alſo one M. <hi>Bellamy,</hi> while he would ſeeme to be Londons Remonſtrating Champion, he has nibbled at me. To whom I ſay,
<list>
                  <item>1. That I am perſwaded I ſtand cleere in his conſcience, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I am in his book.</item>
                  <item>2. If what he objects againſt me be an Error, yet ſurely it hath nothing to doe with the point of Independencie of Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, there is no connection between the one and the other, yet he brings it in to ſhew the Principles of ſuch Independents.</item>
                  <item>3. If it were Independencie, yet it runnes not parallel with thoſe mens opinions he had mentioned before, who (he ſayes) hold, That <hi>If the Parliament have been any way unfaithfull and unſerviceable to the Publique, or but groundedly ſuſpected ſo to be, (which all the world knowes, that knowes theſe mens minds, they will quickly be ready to doe) if in any thing they pleaſe not their Palats, that then thoſe that choſe and ſent them, may have liberty to chooſe more faithfull, able, and better men in their places.</hi> Now (ſayes he) conſider theſe mens Tenets. He charges them to tend to utter confuſion of all order, power, Government in Church and Common-wealth, and I will give you an inſtance (ſayes he) of one, (naming my ſelfe, in my Anſwer to D. <hi>Ferne.</hi>)</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>But will his inſtance reach to that he brings it for, to ſhew me to be one of thoſe men he mentioned before for?</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In that he ſayes of me, doe not I ſay, if the Parliament ſhould grow tyrannicall, particular men cannot help themſelves?</item>
               <item>2. The whole State ſhould ſuffer much before it ſhould help it ſelfe by any wayes of reſiſting.</item>
               <item>3. If you can, ſuppoſe a Parliament ſo far to degenerate.</item>
               <item>4. That they ſhould conſpire to deſtroy the Kingdomes.</item>
               <item>5. That they ſhould aime at themſelves ſo farre, as to poſſeſſe the Lands and riches of the Kingdome to themſelves.</item>
               <item>6. What the Kingdome ſhould doe I determine not, but leave to the light of nature to judge. Now is this parallel to the former
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:113727:16"/>opinion he mentioned, am I one of thoſe men? doth this tend unavoidably to utter confuſion of all order, power, government in Church and Common-weath?</item>
               <item>7. Let M. <hi>Bellamie</hi> firſt give a better Anſwer to that Objection, before he finds fault with mine.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Oh how tedious is it to ſpend time to follow theſe vain men, and that we muſt needs anſwer to theſe peeviſh objections!</p>
            <p>What I have done in a way of juſt Apologie for my ſelfe, you may expect from my Brethren, from ſome very ſhortly, from others as their occaſions ſhall permit, no wayes queſtioning but they are able to ſet themſelves right in the conſciences of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entious men.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, we had rather ſee what you would have, what your Cauſe is, then this vindication of your Perſons.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> We freely grant, the truth is to be regarded a thouſand times more then our Perſons, and did not we beleeve that ſuch a Vindication might be uſefull to make way into your hearts for the receiving the truth, we would never have taken this courſe, but ſhould rather have been willing to have lyen in the duſt, and have truſted God with our names. There is indeed a great complaint in the World that they know not what we would have.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Yet ingenuous Brethren in the Aſſembly have profeſſed that they underſtood what we would have as well as our ſelves, ſo cleare have we been in diſcovering our mindes upon all occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> We have lately in a Committee appoynted by the Lords and Commons for Accommodation, declared what we would have in relation to what already is eſtabliſhed, profeſſing that in all things that we had not mentioned in our deſires for forbearance, we agreed with the rule they had eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> If you would know what we would have, it is ſoon told you. 1. We would have the ruling Power of Miniſters not to extend fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then their paſtorall Charge over their People for the feeding of them by the Word &amp; Sacraments. 2. We would have the Saints ſeparated from the world, not in a negative way only, but in ſome poſitive arguments of ſome work of God upon their hearts that accompanies Salvation, ſo far as man may be able to judge; and that they freely joyn in Spirituall Communion, yet ſo as the rule of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:113727:17"/>edification be obſerv'd amongſt others, that there be a cohabitation in thoſe that joyn, and that all that are fit to be members that doe cohabit doe joyn as much as may be. 3. We would have no co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>active violence uſed againſt ſuch men who carry themſelves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly and peaceably in their differences from others, in ſuch things onely as godly and peaceable men may and doe differ in. Were theſe 3. things granted, we might live together as Brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in peace, and love. Are thoſe the men that are the hinderers of reformation, and the diſturbers of the peace, who would be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with theſe 3. things, and if they cannot have them peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly by the permiſſion of the Magiſtrate, are reſolved to ſit down quietly to ſuffer, or to go to what places in the world liberty may be enjoyed in theſe, and yet muſt theſe be judged the diſturbers of the peace? But while men think there is no way for peace but by forcing all to be of the ſame minde, while they thinke the Civill Sword is an ordinance appoynted by GOD to determine all Controverſies in Divinity, and that men muſt needs be chained together by fines and impriſonments, or elſe there can be no peace; that except all men be of the ſame minde themſelves are of, all will come to confuſion: whilſt theſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples prevaile with men, either there muſt be a baſe ſubjection of mens conſciences to ſlavery, a ſuppreſſion of much truth whilſt they ſeek to ſuppreſſe error, or elſe exceeding diſturbance in the Chriſtian world. Happy thoſe men, their memories ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Not who bluſter, and are violent and furious in forcing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to what they conceive right, for theſe are certainly the diſturbers of our peace; but thoſe who ſhall find out ſome expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent whereby Conſcience may not be enſlaved, truth not ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and yet error not countenanced, the ſpirits of men each to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards other ſweetned, Peace procured, Brotherly love recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſtrengthned, confirmed, for the raiſing up of ſuch for the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God upon ſuch and their endeavours, I ſhall not ceaſe to pray, who am deſirous of nothing more then Truth and Peace: but the Lord rebuke turbulent and violent ſpirits.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:113727:17"/>
            <p>But ſeeing you mention a Committee of Lords and Commons for Accommodation, why did not you joyn in a way of Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation with your Brethren? Nothing would ſatisfie you but a Toleration.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Before there was any Rule eſtabliſhed, we laboured what we could for Accommodation, to get the Rule ſo qualified, that we might come under the ſame Rule with our Brethren, profeſſing that we deſired nothing more; but that we could not effect. It was then pleaded, Let the Rule be firſt ſet, and then we ſhall ſee how neere we can come to it, or where the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence will lye, and then ſome way may be conſidered to Accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate in. But when the Rule was ſet, we knew no way, but to ſhew wherein we could not come up to the Rule, and to deſire forbearance in ſuch and ſuch particulars, which the Order of the Lords and Commons gave us power to doe, which we accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly preſented to the Honourable Committee, profeſſing our ſelves to agree with our Brethren in all Fundamentals in Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and in the ſubſtance of Worſhip according to the Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and with the Reformed Churches as they doe, and for the Rule of Diſcipline that we likewiſe agreed in all other things, except thoſe we mentioned, wherein we deſired forbea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>But you ſay, you would not have the Ruling power of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters goe beyond their Paſtoral Charge for Word and Sacramente; what help then can there be, if the Elders of a Church, or a whole Church ſhall erre?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> The Church is a ſpirituall Society, gathered for ſpirituall ends; it hath within it ſelfe no help againſt ſpirituall evils, but ſpirituall, and theſe can onely prevaile with men ſo far as they are ſpiritual and conſcientious. If the declaring the mind of Chriſt by other Churches, if the proteſting againſt the erring Elders or Churches, and withdrawing Communion from them, will not ſtrike upon Conſcience, what ſhall? Can the adding of an Act of formall Juriſdiction, whoſe Divine Inſtitution few ſee, and is doubted of by thoſe with whom it ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, can that doe it? The former meanes wil remedy evils, if men be conſcientious; the latter will not doe it, if they be not conſcientious.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:113727:18"/>
            <p>If you ſay, The Magiſtrate muſt come in and helpe.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 1. Howſoever then in Church help there is little dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you intereſſe the Magiſtrates power, he muſt then either by himſelfe or by ſome Commiſſioners take cogniſance of the <hi>jus</hi> and the fact, wherein his power is to be exerciſed, he muſt not act upon an implicite beliefe, that the acts of the Church are right.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Will you call in his power in all matters of difference, wherein your ſelves cannot agree? or will you onely deſire his power to help, when either the hainouſneſſe of the matter, or the turbulencie of the carriage, manifeſts ſtubbornneſſe? If in the former caſe, then you make the Magiſtrate the Judge of all Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies in Religion, which I beleeve you are not willing to doe. If in the latter onely, we are agreed. Why then is there ſuch a ſtir, ſuch an out-cry againſt that which is called the Independent way, as if there muſt needs be a confuſion of all things, if liberty in it be granted? The Lord judge between us and our Brethren in this thing: To him we refer our Names and our Cauſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:113727:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
